Finding aid for John Klaerr Walsh papers, 1928-1958
Bentley Historical Library
John Klaerr Walsh papers
1928-1958
Bentley Historical Library
Walsh, John Klaerr, 1887-1964
86190 Aa 2; AC
0.5 linear feet
1 oversize volume
Kalamazoo, Michigan newspaperman; papers relating to his career in journalism and to his trip to the Far East in 1940.
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Eck Stanger (donor no. 5387 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
John K. Walsh was a newspaperman for the Kalamazoo Gazette. In 1940, he was the representative of the Associated Press on a Pan American Clipper flight to the Far East. The purpose of the flight was in part to inaugurate the opening of passenger flights to the Far East and to inform readers about the people, customs, and politics of these countries. The route taken included stops in New Zealand, Australia, Singapore, Saigon, Hong King, Manila, and Honolulu.
The Walsh papers includes scattered materials relating to his career as a newspaperman. The bulk of the collection concerns the flight of American newspapermen aboard a clipper plane to the South Pacific prior to World War II. Other materials relate to the history and operation of the Kalamazoo Gazette. Items of interest include research material concerning Dr. William E. Upjohn and the history of the Upjohn family. There is also correspondence received, 1929-1930, supporting the newspaper's editorial position regarding enforcement of the 18th Amendment. Some of the correspondents in the collection include: Caroline Bartlett Crane, Fred W. Green, Frank Murphy, Chase S. Osborn, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Arthur H. Vandenberg, and Wendell L. Willkie.
Aeronautics.; Journalists -- Michigan -- Kalamazoo.; Kalamazoo (Mich.); Kalamazoo gazette.; American newspapers -- Michigan -- Kalamazoo.; Prohibition -- Michigan.; Oceania.; World War, 1939-1945.; Airplanes.; Australia.; Eating and drinking.; Graduation ceremonies.; Interiors.; Journalism.; Journalists -- Michigan -- Kalamazoo.; Kalamazoo gazette.; Kalamazoo (Mich.); Military art and science.; Newspapers -- Michigan -- Kalamazoo.; Passengers.; Sheep.; Sleeping.; Travel.; Photographs.; Postcards.; Upjohn, William E.; Upjohn family.; Kalamazoo College.; Crane, Caroline Bartlett, 1858-1935.; Green, Fred W. (Fred Warren), 1872-1936.; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), 1860-; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; Willkie, Wendell L. (Wendell Lewis), 1892-1944.
- Newspaper career
  - Correspondence, 1928-1952 (Box 1)
    (include letters, 1929-1930, responding to editorial urging enforcement of 18th Amendment; other correspondents include: Fred W. Green, Caroline Bartlett Crane, Chase S. Osborn, Wendell Willkie)
  - Letters of congratulations, 1936-1937 (Box 1)
    (written on occasion of the centennial celebration of the Kalamazoo Gazette. Correspondents include President Franklin D. Roosevelt, Chase S. Osborn, Arthur H. Vandenberg, Frank Murphy)
  - Research material relating to history of Upjohn family of Kalamazoo (Box 1)
  - Papers 1947-1959, undated, largely concerning the history of the Kalamazoo Gazette (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and newspaper clippings, concerning exhibit sponsored by U.S. Information Agency, staged in Europe on Kalamazoo, Michigan, 1957-1958 (Box 1)
  - Papers, concerning honorary degree received from Kalamazoo College, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Photograph, of the Kalamazoo Gazette copy room, 1920s (Box 1)
- South Pacific tour
  - Correspondence, August-November 1940 (Box 1)
  - Reports, newspaper clippings and observations (Box 1)
  - Maps, routes, and timetables (Box 1)
  - Brochures and miscellanea from South Pacific tour (Box 1)
  - Photographs, of South Pacific tour, 1940 (Box 1)
    (includes members of the tour, military subjects and planes)
  - Photographs, of South Pacific tour, 1940; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook, of South Pacific Tour, 1940 (Volume 1)
    (including clippings containing accounts of visits to New Zealand, Australia, the Netherlands East Indies, Hong Kong, and Manila, and other Pacific military positions.)